<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<protocol name="ext_input_trigger_action_v1">
  <copyright>
    Copyright 2025 Canonical Limited

    Permission is hereby granted, free of charge, to any person obtaining a
    copy of this software and associated documentation files (the "Software"),
    to deal in the Software without restriction, including without limitation
    the rights to use, copy, modify, merge, publish, distribute, sublicense,
    and/or sell copies of the Software, and to permit persons to whom the
    Software is furnished to do so, subject to the following conditions:

    The above copyright notice and this permission notice shall be included in
    all copies or substantial portions of the Software.

    THE SOFTWARE IS PROVIDED "AS IS", WITHOUT WARRANTY OF ANY KIND, EXPRESS OR
    IMPLIED, INCLUDING BUT NOT LIMITED TO THE WARRANTIES OF MERCHANTABILITY,
    FITNESS FOR A PARTICULAR PURPOSE AND NONINFRINGEMENT. IN NO EVENT SHALL
    THE AUTHORS OR COPYRIGHT HOLDERS BE LIABLE FOR ANY CLAIM, DAMAGES OR OTHER
    LIABILITY, WHETHER IN AN ACTION OF CONTRACT, TORT OR OTHERWISE, ARISING FROM,
    OUT OF OR IN CONNECTION WITH THE SOFTWARE OR THE USE OR OTHER DEALINGS IN
    THE SOFTWARE.
  </copyright>

  <description summary="Subscription for global input actions">
    This protocol lets a client react to a global input action. An action is an
    activity (for example "play/pause" or "toggle-launcher") that a privileged
    client has bound to one or more input triggers, such as a key combination,
    using the `ext_input_trigger_registration_v1` protocol.

    A client subscribes by passing a token to
    `ext_input_trigger_action_manager_v1.get_input_trigger_action`. The token
    is issued by the compositor, delivered to the registering client, and then
    passed to interested clients out of band (for example through a desktop
    settings service).

    For example, a media player reacting to the system "play/pause" action:

        # obtain the action's token out of band (e.g. from a settings
        # service), then subscribe to the action
        manager = registry.bind(ext_input_trigger_action_manager_v1)
        action = manager.get_input_trigger_action(token)

        # toggle playback each time the action fires
        on action.begin(time, activation_token):
            player.toggle_play_pause()

        # the action no longer exists; clean up
        on action.unavailable():
            action.destroy()
  </description>

  <interface name="ext_input_trigger_action_manager_v1" version="1">
    <description summary="used to register interest in input actions">
      This global interface allows a Wayland client to register interest in
      input trigger actions. It is advertised by the registry and bound by the
      client.
    </description>

    <enum name="error">
      <entry name="invalid_token" value="1"
        summary="token was not issued by the compositor or has been invalidated"/>
    </enum>

    <request name="destroy" type="destructor">
      <description summary="destroy input trigger action manager object">
        This informs the compositor that the input trigger action manager
        object will no longer be used. Existing objects created through this
        interface remain valid.
      </description>
    </request>

    <request name="get_input_trigger_action">
      <description summary="register interest in input trigger action">
        This request creates an input trigger action object.

        The token should be one issued by the compositor. If the token was not
        issued by the compositor, or is no longer valid, the compositor must
        raise an `invalid_token` protocol error.

        If the token has been issued by the compositor, is still valid, but is
        no longer available, then an `ext_input_trigger_action_v1.unavailable`
        event should be sent immediately.
      </description>
      <arg name="token" type="string" summary="the exported action token"/>
      <arg name="id" type="new_id" interface="ext_input_trigger_action_v1"/>
    </request>
  </interface>

  <interface name="ext_input_trigger_action_v1" version="1">
    <description summary="a subscription to an input trigger action">
      This object is a client's handle to an input trigger action, obtained by
      passing an action token to
      `ext_input_trigger_action_manager_v1.get_input_trigger_action`.

      The compositor notifies the client each time the associated action fires:
      `begin` and `end` are always sent in pairs, with `begin` always preceding
      `end`.

      If the action becomes unavailable the compositor sends the `unavailable`
      event, after which the object is of no further use and should be
      destroyed.
    </description>

    <event name="begin">
      <description summary="begin the input action">
        One of the input triggers associated with the action has occurred.

        The client may begin the activity it associates with the action.

        For keyboard triggers, this will be sent when all keys in the
        corresponding trigger have been pressed.

        The time argument is a timestamp with millisecond granularity, with an
        undefined base. clients must not assume any relation to wall-clock
        time; timestamps are only valid for comparison/deltas.

        The activation token argument is a short-lived opaque token that may be
        used with `xdg_activation_v1` to request to focus another surface.
      </description>
      <arg name="time" type="uint" summary="timestamp with millisecond granularity"/>
      <arg name="activation_token" type="string" summary="an xdg_activation token"/>
    </event>

    <event name="end">
      <description summary="end the input action">
        The input trigger that led to the "begin" event has stopped.

        The client may end (or begin!) the activity it associates with the action.

        For keyboard triggers, this will be sent when any key in the
        corresponding trigger has been released.

        The time argument is a timestamp with millisecond granularity, with an
        undefined base. clients must not assume any relation to wall-clock
        time; timestamps are only valid for comparison/deltas.

        The activation token argument is a short-lived opaque token that may be
        used with `xdg_activation_v1` to request to focus another surface.
      </description>
      <arg name="time" type="uint" summary="timestamp with millisecond granularity"/>
      <arg name="activation_token" type="string" summary="an xdg_activation token"/>
    </event>

    <event name="unavailable">
      <description summary="the input action is no longer available">
        The action this object refers to is, or has become, unavailable, so no
        begin or end events will be delivered. For example, the provider may
        have purged the action with
        `ext_input_trigger_action_control_v1.cancel_and_destroy`, or the token
        may already have been unavailable when this object was created (see
        `ext_input_trigger_action_manager_v1.get_input_trigger_action`).

        This object is of no further use and should be destroyed.
      </description>
    </event>

    <request name="destroy" type="destructor">
      <description summary="destroy the input trigger action">
        This informs the compositor that the input trigger action will no
        longer be used.
      </description>
    </request>
  </interface>
</protocol>
