<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<protocol name="ext_input_trigger_registration_v1">
  <copyright>
    Copyright 2025 Canonical Limited

    Permission is hereby granted, free of charge, to any person obtaining a
    copy of this software and associated documentation files (the "Software"),
    to deal in the Software without restriction, including without limitation
    the rights to use, copy, modify, merge, publish, distribute, sublicense,
    and/or sell copies of the Software, and to permit persons to whom the
    Software is furnished to do so, subject to the following conditions:

    The above copyright notice and this permission notice shall be included in
    all copies or substantial portions of the Software.

    THE SOFTWARE IS PROVIDED "AS IS", WITHOUT WARRANTY OF ANY KIND, EXPRESS OR
    IMPLIED, INCLUDING BUT NOT LIMITED TO THE WARRANTIES OF MERCHANTABILITY,
    FITNESS FOR A PARTICULAR PURPOSE AND NONINFRINGEMENT. IN NO EVENT SHALL
    THE AUTHORS OR COPYRIGHT HOLDERS BE LIABLE FOR ANY CLAIM, DAMAGES OR OTHER
    LIABILITY, WHETHER IN AN ACTION OF CONTRACT, TORT OR OTHERWISE, ARISING FROM,
    OUT OF OR IN CONNECTION WITH THE SOFTWARE OR THE USE OR OTHER DEALINGS IN
    THE SOFTWARE.
  </copyright>

  <description summary="Registration of global input triggers and associated actions">
    This protocol lets a privileged client define global input actions and bind
    them to input triggers, such as key combinations. An action is an activity
    (for example "play/pause" or "toggle-launcher"); a trigger is an input, such
    as "Meta+p", that fires it. When a trigger fires, the client subscribed to
    the action is notified through the `ext_input_trigger_action_v1` protocol.

    The registering client reserves a trigger (obtaining an
    `ext_input_trigger_v1`), creates an action (obtaining an
    `ext_input_trigger_action_control_v1` and, with it, a token), and associates
    triggers with the action. It then delivers the token to interested clients
    out of band (for example through a desktop settings service), which subscribe
    using `ext_input_trigger_action_manager_v1.get_input_trigger_action`.

    For example, binding "Meta+p" to a "play/pause" action:

        # bind the manager global and reserve a key combination
        manager = registry.bind(ext_input_trigger_registration_manager_v1)
        trigger = manager.register_keyboard_sym_trigger(Meta, XKB_KEY_p)

        # create the action and collect its token
        control = manager.get_action_control("play/pause")
        on control.done(token):
            control.add_input_trigger_event(trigger)
            # hand the token to interested clients out of band
            settings_service.publish("play/pause", token)

        # when the user later removes the binding, purge the action
        on user_removes_binding("play/pause"):
            control.cancel_and_destroy()
  </description>

  <interface name="ext_input_trigger_registration_manager_v1" version="1">
    <description summary="used to register input triggers and actions">
      This global interface allows a Wayland client to register ownership of
      input trigger events and associate them with actions. It is advertised by
      the registry and bound by the client.
    </description>

    <enum name="capability" bitfield="true">
      <description summary="the types of inputs that support triggers">
        This is a bitmask of capabilities this system has; if a member is
        set, then triggers can be set.
      </description>
      <entry name="keyboard" value="0x01" summary="key combinations can be used as triggers"/>
    </enum>

    <event name="capabilities">
      <description summary="input trigger capabilities">
        This is emitted when `ext_input_trigger_registration_manager_v1` is
        bound and whenever a system gains or loses the capabilities. The
        argument is a capability enum containing the complete set of
        capabilities.
      </description>
      <arg name="capabilities" type="uint" enum="capability" summary="types of inputs that support triggers"/>
    </event>

    <request name="destroy" type="destructor">
      <description summary="destroy input trigger registration manager object">
        This informs the compositor that the input trigger registration manager
        object will no longer be used. Existing objects created through this
        interface remain valid.
      </description>
    </request>

    <enum name="modifiers" bitfield="true">
      <description summary="modifier keys">
        The various modifiers on the keyboard.
      </description>
      <entry name="alt" value="0x01" summary="any Alt key"/>
      <entry name="alt_left" value="0x02" summary="left Alt key"/>
      <entry name="alt_right" value="0x04" summary="right Alt key"/>
      <entry name="shift" value="0x08" summary="any Shift key"/>
      <entry name="shift_left" value="0x10" summary="left Shift key"/>
      <entry name="shift_right" value="0x20" summary="right Shift key"/>
      <entry name="sym" value="0x40" summary="Sym key"/>
      <entry name="function" value="0x80" summary="Function key"/>
      <entry name="ctrl" value="0x100" summary="any Ctrl key"/>
      <entry name="ctrl_left" value="0x200" summary="left Ctrl key"/>
      <entry name="ctrl_right" value="0x400" summary="right Ctrl key"/>
      <entry name="meta" value="0x800" summary="any Meta key"/>
      <entry name="meta_left" value="0x1000" summary="left Meta key"/>
      <entry name="meta_right" value="0x2000" summary="right Meta key"/>
      <!-- no need for caps/num/scroll lock? -->
    </enum>

    <request name="register_keyboard_sym_trigger">
      <description summary="register a keysym-based input trigger">
        This request creates an input trigger and asks the compositor to reserve
        it to the manager. This allows triggering on a character key combination
        such as "Meta+a".

        As the layout changes, key locations might change. For example, when
        changing between a QWERTY and AZERTY layout, the location of the "Q"
        key will change, and the user will have to press a different physical
        key combination. With non-latin layouts, some key combinations might
        not be available.

        The trigger begins when the combination of modifiers and keysym are
        pressed and ends when that changes. The keysym parameter is interpreted
        according to xkbcommon-keysyms.h.

        The compositor will send either the `ext_input_trigger_v1.done` or
        `ext_input_trigger_v1.failed` event on the created object in
        response to this request.

        Input actions triggered by this request will result in an
        `ext_input_trigger_action_v1.begin` event when the key combination is
        pressed and `ext_input_trigger_action_v1.end` when the key combination
        changes. Key repeats are ignored.
      </description>
      <arg name="modifiers" type="uint" enum="modifiers" summary="bitmask of modifier keys held for the trigger"/>
      <arg name="keysym" type="uint" summary="the key to trigger the action"/>
      <arg name="id" type="new_id" interface="ext_input_trigger_v1"/>
    </request>

    <request name="register_keyboard_code_trigger">
      <description summary="register a keycode-based input trigger">
        This request creates an input trigger and asks the compositor to reserve
        it to the manager. This allows triggering on a specific key combination
        such as "Alt+the-key-above-tab".

        The trigger begins when the combination of modifiers and keycode are
        pressed and ends when that changes.

        The compositor will send either the `ext_input_trigger_v1.done` or
        `ext_input_trigger_v1.failed` event on the created object in
        response to this request.

        Input actions triggered by this request will result in an
        `ext_input_trigger_action_v1.begin` event when the key combination is
        pressed and `ext_input_trigger_action_v1.end` when the key combination
        changes. Key repeats are ignored.
      </description>
      <arg name="modifiers" type="uint" enum="modifiers" summary="bitmask of modifier keys held for the trigger"/>
      <arg name="keycode" type="uint" summary="the key to trigger the action"/>
      <arg name="id" type="new_id" interface="ext_input_trigger_v1"/>
    </request>

    <request name="get_action_control">
      <description summary="get input trigger action control object">
        This request creates an action control object.

        The name parameter describes the action (it has no semantic content and
        may be duplicated across actions).

        The compositor will send the ext_input_trigger_action_control_v1.done event in
        response to this request.
      </description>
      <arg name="name" type="string" summary="a description of the action"/>
      <arg name="id" type="new_id" interface="ext_input_trigger_action_control_v1"/>
    </request>
  </interface>

  <interface name="ext_input_trigger_v1" version="1">
    <description summary="a reserved input trigger">
      This object represents a client's request to reserve an input trigger.
      In response to its creation the compositor must send either the `done`
      or the `failed` event.

      The done event indicates the trigger is now owned by the manager: the
      compositor will not allow this or any other manager to register the same
      trigger. The reservation lasts until the object is destroyed, which
      releases the trigger.

      The failed event indicates the trigger could not be owned by the manager,
      for example because it is already reserved. The object is then of no
      further use and should be destroyed.
    </description>

    <request name="destroy" type="destructor">
      <description summary="destroy the input trigger">
        This informs the compositor that the input trigger will no longer be
        used.
      </description>
    </request>

    <event name="done">
      <description summary="input trigger successfully registered">
        This client is now responsible for handling this input trigger.
      </description>
    </event>

    <event name="failed">
      <description summary="input trigger failed to register">
        The failed event indicates that the trigger is not "owned" by the manager.
        This means the object is of no further use and should be destroyed.
      </description>
    </event>
  </interface>

  <interface name="ext_input_trigger_action_control_v1" version="1">
    <description summary="an input trigger action">
      This object represents an input trigger action owned by this client. The
      action associates one or more input triggers with a token that other
      clients can use, via the `ext_input_trigger_action_v1` protocol, to be
      notified when the action fires.

      In response to the creation of this object the compositor must send the
      done event, which delivers the action's token. Triggers are associated
      with the action using `add_input_trigger_event` and
      `drop_input_trigger_event`.

      Destroying the object with `cancel_and_destroy` purges the action, while
      destroy leaves it intact; see those requests for details.
    </description>

    <request name="add_input_trigger_event">
      <description summary="add an input trigger to the action">
        This request adds an input trigger to those that activate the action.
      </description>
      <arg name="trigger" type="object" interface="ext_input_trigger_v1" summary="the trigger being added"/>
    </request>

    <request name="drop_input_trigger_event">
      <description summary="drop an input trigger from the action">
        This request drops an input trigger from those that activate the action.
      </description>
      <arg name="trigger" type="object" interface="ext_input_trigger_v1" summary="the trigger being dropped"/>
    </request>

    <event name="done">
      <description summary="action registered and token issued">
        This event delivers the action's token. It is sent once, immediately
        after the object is created.

        The action token is usable by the `ext_input_trigger_action_manager_v1`
        protocol to get handles to actions via
        `ext_input_trigger_action_manager_v1.get_input_trigger_action`. The
        token can be used by this or another client (or clients).

        The token expires a short, implementation-defined time after this event
        is sent, whether or not it has been used; using it does not extend its
        lifetime. A client should therefore use the token, or hand it to
        another client, promptly. After it expires, passing it to
        `ext_input_trigger_action_manager_v1.get_input_trigger_action` raises
        an `invalid_token` protocol error.
      </description>
      <arg name="token" type="string" summary="the exported action token"/>
    </event>

    <request name="cancel_and_destroy" type="destructor">
      <description summary="purge the input trigger action and destroy this object">
        This purges the input trigger action and destroys this object. It would
        typically be used when the user deletes the input trigger the action
        represents.

        The action itself ceases to exist: every `ext_input_trigger_action_v1`
        that was created from this action's token (by this or any other client)
        is notified with an `ext_input_trigger_action_v1.unavailable` event and
        will receive no further begin or end events.

        To destroy this object while leaving the action (and any
        `ext_input_trigger_action_v1` objects derived from it) intact, use
        destroy instead.
      </description>
    </request>

    <request name="destroy" type="destructor">
      <description summary="destroy this object but leave the action intact">
        This destroys this object without purging the input trigger action. The
        action continues to exist: any `ext_input_trigger_action_v1` created
        from its token (by this or any other client) is unaffected and keeps
        receiving begin and end events.

        To purge the action and make those objects unavailable, use
        `cancel_and_destroy` instead.
      </description>
    </request>
  </interface>
</protocol>
