<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<protocol name="ext-lockscreen_v1">
  <copyright>    
    Copyright © Canonical Ltd.

    This program is free software: you can redistribute it and/or modify it
    under the terms of the GNU General Public License version 2 or 3,
    as published by the Free Software Foundation.

    This program is distributed in the hope that it will be useful,
    but WITHOUT ANY WARRANTY; without even the implied warranty of
    MERCHANTABILITY or FITNESS FOR A PARTICULAR PURPOSE.  See the
    GNU General Public License for more details.
    
    You should have received a copy of the GNU General Public License
    along with this program.  If not, see <http://www.gnu.org/licenses/>.
  </copyright>
  <description summary="compositor authoritative screen-locking mechanism">
    This protocol allows for a priveleged Wayland client to display arbitrary graphics
    on the screen when the compositor informs the client that the session has been
    locked.

    The compositor may choose to restrict this protocol to a special client
    launched by the compositor itself or expose it to all privileged clients.
    This is up to the compositor policy.

    The compositor is responsible for deciding when the session should be locked and unlocked.
    If the client dies while the session is locked, the client may simply resubmit
    a buffer for display at a later time. During this time, the compositor itself
    may have been unlocked via some other mechanism (e.g. loginctl). Exactly how and
    when the compositor locks and unlocks is the policy of the compositor.

    A typical use case is for the compositor to lock or unlock when it receives a
    signal from Logind to do so.

    The key words "must", "must not", "required", "shall", "shall not",
    "should", "should not", "recommended",  "may", and "optional" in this
    document are to be interpreted as described in IETF RFC 2119.
  </description>

  <interface name="ext_lockscreen_manager_v1" version="1">
    <description summary="used to create lockscreen surfaces">
      
    </description>
    <request name="associate">
      This request creates a lockscreen surface and asks the compositor to show this
      surface on the provided output when the session is next locked. If the session is
      already locked, the compositor will display this surface right away.

      Surfaces may display different content on different outputs.
      
      This surface will be shown immediately after the session is locked. It is expected
      that the compositor does not render intermediary content if a lockscreen surface
      is provided for an output. If a surface is NOT provided for an output, then it is up to the
      policy of the compositor to render what it wants.

      The client is expected to destroy lockscreen surfaces as outputs are removed.
      The client is expected to associate lockscreen surfaces as outputs are added.

      Associating more than one surface for an output is a duplicate_surface error.
      Associating a surface with a null buffer is a null_buffer error.
      
      <arg name="id" type="new_id" interface="ext_lockscreen_surface_v1"/>
      <arg name="surface" type="object" interface="wl_surface"/>
      <arg name="output" type="object" interface="wl_output"/>
    </request>

    <enum name="error">
      <entry name="duplicate_surface" value="0"
             summary="attempted to associate more than once surface as the lockscreen surface for an output"/>
      <entry name="null_buffer" value="1"
        summary="surface committed with a null buffer"/>
    </enum>
  </interface>

  <interface name="ext_lockscreen_surface_v1" version="1">
    <request name="destroy" type="destructor">
      This informs the compositor that the lockscreen surface object will no longer be
      used.

      If the session is locked when this happens, the compositor will display a default
      render of its choosing until the session is unlocked.
    </request>
    
    <event name="locked">
      This event is sent when the compositor decides to lock the session.
      At this time, the compositor will show the surface.
    </event>
    <event name="unlocked">
      This event is sent when the compositor decides to unlock the session.
      At this time, the compositor will hide the surface.
    </event>
    <event name="configure">
      This event is sent when the lockscreen surface is first created and anytime that the
      dimensions of the output changes after that. The client may use the width and height
      to update their buffer to fit the output dimensions.

      The width and height are in surface-local coordinates. The client is allowed to ignore
      the dimensions.
      <arg name="width" type="uint"/>
      <arg name="height" type="uint"/>
    </event>
  </interface>
</protocol>
