<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<protocol name="mir_application_switcher_unstable_v1">
  <copyright>
    Copyright © 2025 Canonical Limited

    Permission to use, copy, modify, distribute, and sell this
    software and its documentation for any purpose is hereby granted
    without fee, provided that the above copyright notice appear in
    all copies and that both that copyright notice and this permission
    notice appear in supporting documentation, and that the name of
    the copyright holders not be used in advertising or publicity
    pertaining to distribution of the software without specific,
    written prior permission.  The copyright holders make no
    representations about the suitability of this software for any
    purpose.  It is provided "as is" without express or implied
    warranty.

    THE COPYRIGHT HOLDERS DISCLAIM ALL WARRANTIES WITH REGARD TO THIS
    SOFTWARE, INCLUDING ALL IMPLIED WARRANTIES OF MERCHANTABILITY AND
    FITNESS, IN NO EVENT SHALL THE COPYRIGHT HOLDERS BE LIABLE FOR ANY
    SPECIAL, INDIRECT OR CONSEQUENTIAL DAMAGES OR ANY DAMAGES
    WHATSOEVER RESULTING FROM LOSS OF USE, DATA OR PROFITS, WHETHER IN
    AN ACTION OF CONTRACT, NEGLIGENCE OR OTHER TORTIOUS ACTION,
    ARISING OUT OF OR IN CONNECTION WITH THE USE OR PERFORMANCE OF
    THIS SOFTWARE.
  </copyright>

  <interface name="mir_application_switcher_v1" version="1">
    <description summary="application switcher client responsibilities">
      Clients may use this interface to declare themselves as the application
      switcher. An "application switcher" is a client that is responsible for
      cycling through applications or windows that need focus, typically on the
      "alt + tab" and "alt + tick" keybinds.

      As an application switcher, the client is notified when it should display
      itself and in what state it should do so.

      It is the responsibility of the client to use other protocols (e.g.
      wlr foreign toplevel management) to list the available windows and applications
      and request activation on them when appropriate.

      Only one application switcher may be registered at any time.
    </description>

    <request name="create">
      <description summary="create a new mir_application_switcher_handle_v1">
        Request to become the application switcher.

        Attempting to register an application switcher while another mir_application_switcher_handle_v1
        client is valid is a client error.
      </description>

      <arg name="id" type="new_id" interface="mir_application_switcher_handle_v1"/>
    </request>

    <enum name="error">
      <entry name="already_set" value="0" summary="application switcher already set"/>
    </enum>
  </interface>

  <interface name="mir_application_switcher_handle_v1" version="1">
    <event name="activate">
      Requests that the application switcher client activates.

      The client may choose to respond to this event however they deem fit.
      For example, they may display an overlay layer shell surface and begin
      submitting visible buffers to it while waiting on further key events.

      If the application switcher is already active, then nothing happens.

      This request may be sent in response to a keystroke or anything else that the shell
      decides.

      The initial state argument provides the client with information about the type of
      focus switching that is currently happening. Focus switching may happen either across
      all applications or within an application. The focus switching direction may be forwards
      or backwards. The client may choose to do whatever it deems necessary in response to
      this argument.

      <arg name="initial_state" type="uint" enum="state" summary="initial state of the application switcher"/>
    </event>

    <event name="deactivate">
      Requests that the application switcher deactivates.

      The client may choose to respond to this event however they deem fit.
      For example, they may hide their surfaces and stop listening on keystrokes.

      If the application switcher is already inactive, then nothing happens.
    </event>

    <event name="state">
      Informs the client that the type of focus switching has changed.

      This event may be sent in response to a keystroke or anything else that the shell
      decides.

      The client may choose to do whatever it deems necessary in response.

      <arg name="state" type="uint" enum="state" summary="new state of the application switcher"/>
    </event>

    <event name="next">
      Informs the client that it should tentatively focus the next item in the focus order.
      The "next" item is up to the client to decide, but it is often the next window or application
      given in the focus order per the current state.

      The client may choose to do whatever it deems necessary in response.
    </event>

    <event name="confirm">
      Informs the client that it should focus the tentatively selected item.
    </event>

    <request name="destroy" type="destructor">
      <description summary="destroy the mir_application_switcher_handle_v1 object">
        Notify the compositor that the mir_application_switcher_handle_v1 will no longer
        be used.

        Once received by the compositor, the compositor should be able to register a new
        mir_application_switcher_handle_v1 without throwing an error.
      </description>
    </request>

    <enum name="state">
      <entry name="all_forward" value="0" summary="cycling across applications going forward"/>
      <entry name="all_backward" value="1" summary="cycling across applications going backward"/>
      <entry name="within_forward" value="2" summary="cycling within the current application going forward"/>
      <entry name="within_backward" value="3" summary="cycling within the current application going backward"/>
    </enum>
  </interface>

</protocol>