<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<protocol name="xdg_dialog_v1">

  <copyright>
    Copyright © 2023 Carlos Garnacho

    Permission is hereby granted, free of charge, to any person obtaining a
    copy of this software and associated documentation files (the "Software"),
    to deal in the Software without restriction, including without limitation
    the rights to use, copy, modify, merge, publish, distribute, sublicense,
    and/or sell copies of the Software, and to permit persons to whom the
    Software is furnished to do so, subject to the following conditions:

    The above copyright notice and this permission notice (including the next
    paragraph) shall be included in all copies or substantial portions of the
    Software.

    THE SOFTWARE IS PROVIDED "AS IS", WITHOUT WARRANTY OF ANY KIND, EXPRESS OR
    IMPLIED, INCLUDING BUT NOT LIMITED TO THE WARRANTIES OF MERCHANTABILITY,
    FITNESS FOR A PARTICULAR PURPOSE AND NONINFRINGEMENT. IN NO EVENT SHALL
    THE AUTHORS OR COPYRIGHT HOLDERS BE LIABLE FOR ANY CLAIM, DAMAGES OR OTHER
    LIABILITY, WHETHER IN AN ACTION OF CONTRACT, TORT OR OTHERWISE, ARISING
    FROM, OUT OF OR IN CONNECTION WITH THE SOFTWARE OR THE USE OR OTHER
    DEALINGS IN THE SOFTWARE.
  </copyright>

  <interface name="xdg_wm_dialog_v1" version="1">
    <description summary="create dialogs related to other toplevels">
      The xdg_wm_dialog_v1 interface is exposed as a global object allowing
      to create xdg_dialog_v1 objects. These objects can be used to
      coordinate the creation of dialogs relative to another toplevel.

      Warning! The protocol described in this file is currently in the testing
      phase. Backward compatible changes may be added together with the
      corresponding interface version bump. Backward incompatible changes can
      only be done by creating a new major version of the extension.
    </description>

    <enum name="error">
      <description summary="error values for this object"/>
      <entry name="already_used" value="0"
             summary="the xdg_toplevel object has already been used to create a xdg_dialog_v1"/>
    </enum>

    <request name="destroy" type="destructor">
      <description summary="destroy the dialog manager object">
        Destroys the xdg_wm_dialog_v1 object. This does not affect
        the xdg_dialog_v1 objects created from it.
      </description>
    </request>

    <request name="get_xdg_dialog">
      <description summary="create a dialog object">
        Create a new dialog object associated with the given toplevel, to
        allow managing dialogs.

        Only one xdg_dialog_v1 may exist for each xdg_toplevel. If an
        xdg_dialog_v1 already exists for the given xdg_toplevel, the
        already_used error is raised.
      </description>
      <arg name="id" type="new_id" interface="xdg_dialog_v1"/>
      <arg name="toplevel" type="object" interface="xdg_toplevel"/>
    </request>
  </interface>

  <interface name="xdg_dialog_v1" version="1">
    <description summary="dialog object">
      A dialog object is associated to a xdg_toplevel. It allows the
      compositor to treat the toplevel as a dialog and apply dialog-specific
      policies.

      Compositors may treat dialogs differently from regular windows in many
      ways, e.g. refusing to iconify or maximize them. The user can usually
      dismiss a dialog by pressing a dedicated key (e.g. Escape).
    </description>

    <request name="destroy" type="destructor">
      <description summary="destroy the dialog object">
        Destroys the xdg_dialog_v1 object. This does not affect
        the dialog state on the associated xdg_toplevel.
      </description>
    </request>

    <request name="set_modal">
      <description summary="mark dialog as modal">
        Hint that the dialog has modal behavior. See the description of
        xdg_dialog_v1 for more details about what is expected from
        modal dialogs.

        This request does not take effect for an unmapped toplevel.
      </description>
    </request>

    <request name="unset_modal">
      <description summary="mark dialog as not modal">
        Hint that the dialog does not have modal behavior. See the description
        of xdg_dialog_v1 for more details.

        This request does not take effect for an unmapped toplevel.
      </description>
    </request>
  </interface>

</protocol>
