<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<protocol name="mir_window_management_unstable_v1">

  <copyright>
    Copyright © 2020 William Wold

    Permission is hereby granted, free of charge, to any person obtaining a
    copy of this software and associated documentation files (the "Software"),
    to deal in the Software without restriction, including without limitation
    the rights to use, copy, modify, merge, publish, distribute, sublicense,
    and/or sell copies of the Software, and to permit persons to whom the
    Software is furnished to do so, subject to the following conditions:

    The above copyright notice and this permission notice (including the next
    paragraph) shall be included in all copies or substantial portions of the
    Software.

    THE SOFTWARE IS PROVIDED "AS IS", WITHOUT WARRANTY OF ANY KIND, EXPRESS OR
    IMPLIED, INCLUDING BUT NOT LIMITED TO THE WARRANTIES OF MERCHANTABILITY,
    FITNESS FOR A PARTICULAR PURPOSE AND NONINFRINGEMENT.  IN NO EVENT SHALL
    THE AUTHORS OR COPYRIGHT HOLDERS BE LIABLE FOR ANY CLAIM, DAMAGES OR OTHER
    LIABILITY, WHETHER IN AN ACTION OF CONTRACT, TORT OR OTHERWISE, ARISING
    FROM, OUT OF OR IN CONNECTION WITH THE SOFTWARE OR THE USE OR OTHER
    DEALINGS IN THE SOFTWARE.
  </copyright>

  <interface name="zmir_wm_base_v1" version="1">
    <description summary="use enhanced Mir window management features">
      The mir_wm_base interface is exposed as a global object enabling clients
      to fine tune the behavior of windows created with other protocols.
    </description>

    <request name="destroy" type="destructor">
      <description summary="destroy xdg_wm_base">
        Destroy this mir_wm_base object. Objects created with this object are
        unaffected
      </description>
    </request>

    <request name="get_shell_surface">
      <description summary="create a mir_shell_surface object for an existing surface">
          This creates a new mir_shell_surface object that can be used to set Mir
          window management hints on an existing shell surface.

          The hints will only have an effect once the surface is mapped with
          a shell surface role from another protocol (such as xdg_surface)
      </description>
      <arg name="id" type="new_id" interface="zmir_shell_surface_v1"/>
      <arg name="surface" type="object" interface="wl_surface"/>
    </request>
  </interface>

  <interface name="zmir_shell_surface_v1" version="1">
    <description summary="allows specializing a shell surface">
      A mir_shell_surface allows setting Mir-specific properties for an exisitng
      shell surface (such as surface type). This is NOT a surface role. The
      surface should have a shell surface roll from another protocol (such as
      xdg_surface).
    </description>

    <enum name="error">
      <entry name="invalid_window_type" value="0"
        summary="given window type is not valid for window"/>
    </enum>

    <enum name="window_type">
      <entry name="default" value="0" summary="the role's default type'"/>
      <entry name="satellite" value="1"
        summary="an accessory window such as a toolbox'"/>
    </enum>

    <request name="destroy" type="destructor">
      <description summary="destroy the mir_shell_surface object">
        Notify the compositor that the zmir_shell_surface_v1 will no longer be used.
      </description>
    </request>

    <request name="set_window_type">
      <description summary="set the surface's window type">
        The window type affects various aspects of the surface's behavior. This
        state is double-buffered and will be applied next wl_surface.commit.
      </description>
      <arg name="type" type="uint" enum="window_type" summary="window type"/>
    </request>
  </interface>
</protocol>
